Guide to the Pitt Players Records, 1914-1961 CTC.1978.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pitt Players Records
1914-1961
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Pitt Players
CTC.1978.01
1 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Pitt Players were a University of Pittsburgh student theatre group that operated between 1914-1960. This collection contains programs, photographs and other materials related to their performances. Digital reproductions of the Pitt Players programs and selected photographs are available online.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically. Links to digitized images of the individual programs are available in the Collection Inventory; selected photographs were scanned and added to the University of Pittsburgh Historic Photographs collection.
Scope and Content Notes
The Pitt Players were a University of Pittsburgh student theatre group that operated between 1914-1960. This collection contains programs, photographs and other materials related to their performances.
Previous Citation
Pitt Players Records, 1914-1961, CTC.1978.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Pitt Players Records, 1914-1961, CTC.05, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Arrangement
I. Programs
II. Photographs
III. Newspaper clippings
IV. Marketing and other materials
History
The Pitt Players was a student theatre organization at the University of Pittsburgh. They evolved from the Thespian Society, which was the former theatre group before the University moved the campus to Oakland. The founder of the Pitt Players was faculty member George M .P. Baird. He financed, directed, and wrote several of the early plays. Deirdre, by William Butler Yeats, was their first production in 1914; it was performed in Trees gymnasium. The student members of the Players made their own costumes, built their own minimalist sets, and also helped to finance their shows. Their early performances were credited in the newspapers as some of the first experimental theatre productions in the city.
Each season, beginning in the fall, consisted of three or four plays. Each play would be performed between three to six times. Some performances were reserved for University of Pittsburgh students and faculty only. Occasionally, they would perform matinees for area high school students. Productions were halted during World War I, in part due to Baird's enlistment in the service. Pitt Players resumed in 1919 under the direction of Reginald Johnson. Starting in the 1930s, one or two additional productions were offered during the summer. Harvey J. Pope became the director of both the Cap and Gown Club and the Pitt Players in 1947. Before the construction of the Stephen Foster Memorial building, the Pitt Players performed at several locations and venues in Pittsburgh including the Irene Kaufmann Settlement, Heinz House, the Young Men's Hebrew Association, Falk School, Frick Training School, the Schenley Hotel's theater, and the Pittsburgh Playhouse. After 1937, nearly every performance was offered in the Stephen Foster Memorial building. When the Cap and Gown Club was disbanded in 1948, the Pitt Players began to incorporate the musical comedies that made the Cap and Gown Club so popular. The Department of Speech began offering theatre classes as part of their curriculum in 1960. As a result, the Pitt Players dissolved as an extracurricular student group and melded into the University's official theatre troupe. The student actors and actresses were still occasionally referred to as the Pitt Players, but soon even the name faded. In 1982 the Department of Theatre Arts was created and in 1999 the theatre company was named the University of Pittsburgh Repertory Theatre or Pitt Rep.
Related Material
Cap and Gown Club Records, 1908-1978, CTC.1980.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
George M.P. Baird Papers, ca. 1915-1960, CTC.1970.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
University of Pittsburgh Department of Theatre Arts Records, Archives & Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Performing arts -- Study and teaching -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Theater -- Study and teaching -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Theater; Clippings (Information artifacts); Theater programs; Photographs; College and school drama, American -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; College theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh. Department of Speech and Theatre Arts; University of Pittsburgh. Pitt Players
- Programs, 1916-1960; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The Pitt Players programs are arranged in chronological order. Starting with the 1940-1941 season, each season is housed in its' own individual folder.
  - Program chronology (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 1916-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Marriage, April 1916; 1.
    - An English May Day, June 13, 1916; 2.
    - The Lovers of Allianora, April 27, 1917; 3.
    - The New Poor, December 4, 1924; 4.
    - The Torch-Bearers, February 1925; 5.
    - The Dover Road, May 16, 1925; 6.
  - Programs, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dulcy, March 1926; 1.
    - Fashion, April 9, 1926; 2.
    - The Best People, 1928; 3.
    - The Pillars of Society, 1929; 4.
    - The Cradle Song, 1929; 5.
    - The Meanest Man in the World, 1929
    - The Truth About Blayds, March 13, 1930; 6.
    - The Whiteheaded Boy, November 20, 1930; 7.
  - Programs, 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Captain Applejack, February 19, 1931; 1.
    - Alice Sit By The Fire, May 14, 1931; 2.
    - Four One Act Plays, July 29, 1931; 3.
    - He Who Gets Slapped, November 19, 1931; 4.
    - The Swan, February 17, 1932; 5.
    - Hay Fever, May 19, 1932; 6.
    - Enter Madame, November 17, 1932; 7.
    - Craig's Wife, February 16, 1933; 8.
    - Minick, April 6, 1933; 9.
    - The Queen's Husband, November 16, 1933; 10.
    - The Torch-Bearers, March 28, 1934; 11.
    - Children of the Moon, February 15, 1934; 12.
    - March Hares, April 1935; 13.
    - The First Mrs. Fraser, November 1936
    - A Square Peg, February 1937
    - Holiday, 1938-1939; 14.
    - Ceiling Zero, 1938-1939; 15.
    - Brother Rat, 1938-1939; 16.
    - Our Town, May 1939; 17.
    - Three Men on a Horse, November 1939; 18.
    - Counsellor-At-Law, December 1939; 19.
    - You Can't Take It With You, May 1940; 20.
  - Programs, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - My Heart's in the Highlands, November 1940; 1.
    - High Tor, December 1940; 2.
    - Golden Boy, March 1941; 3.
  - Programs, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Yellow Jacket, October 1941; 1.
    - Flight to the West, December 1941; 2.
    - The Women, March 1942; 3.
  - Programs, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Knickerbocker Holiday, March 1943; 1.
    - Echoes of Other Years, August 5, 1943; 2.
  - Programs, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Furlough, but not Furlong, May 1944; 1.
    - Two One-Act Plays, July 27, 1944; 2.
  - Programs, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hedda Gabler, March 1945; 1.
    - Tonight at Eight, November-December 1944; 2.
  - Programs, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jim Dandy, April 1946; 1.
  - Programs, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Room Service, March 1947; 1.
    - Joan of Lorraine, 1947; 2.
  - Programs, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - George Washington Slept Here, November 1947; 1.
    - Outward Bound, July 1948; 2.
  - Programs, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - All My Sons, March 1948; 1.
    - Curtain Time, April 1948; 2.
    - The Would-Be Gentleman, May 1948; 3.
    - The Philadelphia Story, October 1948; 4.
    - The Flies, December 1948; 5.
    - Candida, March 1949; 6.
    - Dark of the Moon, May 1949; 7.
    - The Winslow Boy, July 1949; 8.
  - Programs, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Arsenic and Old Lace, November 1949; 1.
    - Caste, December 1949; 2.
    - Julius Caesar, March 1950; 3.
    - A Connecticut Yankee, May 1950; 4.
    - The Glass Menagerie, August 1950; 5.
  - Programs, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - My Sister Eileen, November 1950; 1.
    - Beggar on Horseback, January 1951; 2.
    - Suspect, March 1951; 3.
    - Gold in the Hills, May 1951
    - Henry IV, August 1951; 4.
  - Programs, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - January Thaw, November 1951; 1.
    - Oedipus Rex, December 1951; 2.
    - You Touched Me, March 1952; 3.
    - Come Back, Little Sheba, July-August 1952; 4.
  - Programs, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Time of Your Life, October 1952; 1.
    - The Heiress, December 1952; 2.
    - Billy Budd, March 1953; 3.
    - Blithe Spirit, May 1953; 4.
    - Yes, M' Lord, July-August 1953; 5.
  - Programs, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Androcles and the Lion, October 1953; 1.
    - The Male Animal, December 1953; 2.
    - The Glass Harp, March 1954; 3.
    - Yes, M' Lord, May 1954; 4.
    - The Man, July 1954; 5.
  - Programs, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Harvey, October 1954; 1.
    - The Great Big Doorstep, December 1954; 2.
    - The Innocents, March 1955; 3.
    - Dark of the Moon, April 1955; 4.
    - The Corn is Green, August 1955; 5.
  - Programs, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Bernardine, November 1955; 1.
    - The Madwoman of Chaillot, January 1956; 2.
    - Mister Roberts, March 1956; 3.
    - Pygmalion, April 1956; 4.
    - Pitt Players Award Banquet, May 23, 1956; 5.
    - Picnic, August 1956; 6.
    - Picnic, 1956; 7.
  - Programs, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Man Who Came to Dinner, November 1956; 1.
    - The Taming of the Shrew, February 1957; 2.
    - Stalag 17, March 1957; 3.
    - Brigadoon, April 1957; 4.
    - The Chalk Garden, August 1957; 5.
    - The Chalk Garden, August 24, 1957; 6.
  - Programs, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Bus Stop, October 1957; 1.
    - Pitt Portraits, November 20, 1957; 2.
    - The Skin of Our Teeth, December 1957; 3.
    - The Teahouse of the August Moon, March 1958; 4.
    - A Phoenix Too Frequent, May 1958; 5.
    - The Happy Time, August 1958; 6.
    - The Happy Time, August 9, 1958; 7.
  - Programs, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - The Would-Be Invalid, October 1958; 1.
    - The Rainmaker, December 1958; 2.
    - Guys and Dolls, March 1959; 3.
    - Our Town, May 1959; 4.
    - Arms and the Man, August 8, 1959; 5.
    - Arms and the Man, August 1959; 6.
  - Programs, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - My Three Angels, December 1959; 1.
    - The Pajama Game, March 1960; 2.
  - Programs, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Time of Your Life, October 1960; 1.
    - The Boy Friend, March 1961; 2.
  - Programs - no dates (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Photographs, 1933-1959; II.
  This series of photographs is arranged in chronological order. They contain stage production photos, rehearsal photos, and headshots of the actors and actresses of the Pitt Players. Some were selected for digitization and are available online as part of the University of Pittsburgh Historic Photographs collection.
  - Craig's Wife, February 1933 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Theta Alpha Phi, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pitt Players, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Buell Whitehill, ca. 1939 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ceiling Zero, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Three Men on a Horse, November 1939 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Counselor-at-Law, December 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Brother Rat, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Adding Machine, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - You Can't Take it With You, May 1940 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - My Heart's in the Highland, November 1940 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - High Tor, December 1940 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Golden Boy, March 1941 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - the Yellow Jacket, October 1941 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Christmas Pageant, December 1941 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Flight to the West, December 1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - the Women, March 1942 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hedda Gabler, March 1945 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Photographs, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - the Philadelphia Story, October 1948 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - the Flies, December 1948 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Candida, March 1949 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Dark of the Moon, May 1949 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Julius Caesar, March 1950 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Mr. Roberts, March 1956 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Picnic, August 1956 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Brigadoon, April 1957 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Skin of Our Teeth, December 1957 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Guys and Dolls, March 1959 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 42-45)
  - Unidentified headshots (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Marketing and Other Materials, 1922-1961; III.
  - Activities fair - advertisements, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Awards, 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Cartoons and other promotional materials, 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cecil B. DeMille visit - clippings and photographs, November 1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Four Jacks and a Queen script, May 15, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Notes on the dramatic activity of Pitt Players, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Press releases, 1954-55 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1947-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1948-49 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Set designs - Adding Machine, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1914-1960; IV.
  The newspaper clippings in this series are arranged in chronological order by season. Clippings relating to the first thirty years of the Pitt Players are few, but starting with the 1947-1948 season, each season is housed in its' own individual folder. Unfortunately, many of the clippings are not properly labeled with the title of the newspaper that it was clipped from. It is believed that the majority of clippings came from the Pitt News.
  - Clippings, 1914-1915 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1938-1942 (Box 3, Folder 14-17)
  - Clippings, 1947-1960 (Box 3, Folder 18-29)
  - Clippings - no dates (Box 3, Folder 30)